<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The propheticall intelligencer, shewing the causes why all corrupt churches of Christendome shall passe away, or depart; and all their sees of corrupt doctrine and discipline shall be abolished, and that the holy city of the church of new Jerusalem is now comming down from my God out of Heaven.</title>
            <author>I. E.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82521</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E404_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201854</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862343</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862343</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114500</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82521)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114500)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 64:E404[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The propheticall intelligencer, shewing the causes why all corrupt churches of Christendome shall passe away, or depart; and all their sees of corrupt doctrine and discipline shall be abolished, and that the holy city of the church of new Jerusalem is now comming down from my God out of Heaven.</title>
                  <author>I. E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Simmons, and are to be sold by John Hancocke in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Written by I.E. Pastor of the New Jerusalem.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114500:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Propheticall INTELLIGENCER, Shewing The cauſes why all corrupt Churches of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome ſhall paſſe away, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; and all their Sees of corrupt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline ſhall be aboliſhed, and that the holy City of the Church of new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is now comming down from my God out of HEAVEN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Simmons,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>John Hancocke</hi> in Popeſ-head Alley, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114500:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114500:2"/>
            <head>The Propheticall Intelligencer, ſhewing the cauſes why all corrupt Churches of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall paſſe away, or depart; and all their Sees of corrupt Doctrine, and Diſcipline ſhall be aboliſhed, and that the holy City of the Church of new Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem is now comming downe from my God out of Heaven.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Revel. 21.1.</bibl> And I ſaw a new Heaven, and a new Earth, for the firſt heaven, and the firſt earth were paſſed away, and there was no more Sea.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome falſely gather, that this is to be underſtood of the Church Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, after the reſurrection, but what need the Church then to be deſcribed, to be comming downe from heaven? it ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſeene going up to it. And what need ſhall there be of gates, a Wall, and City, and a Tree, when all the Saints ſhall be as the Angels of God in heaven? and equall unto them? <hi>Math.</hi> 22. <hi>Luke</hi> 20 But the Holy Ghoſt doth not paint out unto us here, that Angelical happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Saints to come. For it is ſpoken of matters to be done in this life upon earth, as the ſequell shall declare, for it is ſpoken of a new church that shall be upon earth. For the glory of the heavenly, and pure Church, cannot bee ſeene, nor conceived off the heart of a mortall man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. Neither can it be ſet forth with words of compariſons of earthly things, but ſeeing it ſhall be an heavenly Church, therefore the glory and dignity of it, is commended in heavenly things, and yet the deſcription thereof maketh a way to comprehend in our mindes, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly felicity, for if the glory of the Spouſe be ſo great upon earth, what manner of things, and how excellent are thoſe which God have prepared for his Saints, in the fulneſſe of joy? truely our mindes are too dull, and dimme, to meditate of theſe things, let us turne our eyes to contemplate of this bleſſed paradiſe, which ſhall openly be ſeene in the world, as 2 <hi>Eſdras</hi> 8.52. For unto you is paradiſe opened, the tree of life is planted, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.7. The time to come is prepared, plenteouſneſſe made ready, the City builded, <hi>v.</hi> 18. and reſt prepared, perfect goodneſſe, and abſolute wiſedome, the root of evill is ſealed up unto you, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and moth is deſtroyed from you, and into hell fleeth corruption to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. Sorrowes are vaniſhed away, and in the end is ſhewed the treaſure of immortalitie, <hi>v.</hi> 4. I follow him as he goeth with Scripure.</p>
            <p>Now the interpretation of the new heaven, may be taken out of <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.26. whoſe voyce did then ſhake the earth, but now he hath denounced, ſaying, yet once more will I ſhake, not the earth onely but alſo heaven, where to ſhake heaven and earth, is by the interpretation of the Apoſtle, to abrogate the former Church wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, &amp; Temple, to caſt off the earthly people, of all Nations, that would not receive him by a New birth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Io.</hi> 3.3. And ſo he will caſt off all people that are earthly, of all Nations whether of the Churches, or heathen, that will not receive his counſell to buy of him gould, tried in the fire, to make them rich. 1.<note place="margin">Rev. 3.18.</note> The live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114500:3"/>
faith of the merits of Chriſts death in our baptiſme for remiſſion of ſinnes, and white raiment (juſtification) to cloth them, that the ſhame of their nakedneſſe might not appeare, and eye ſalve of the ſpirit in the ſcriptures, that men may ſee Heaven is by a borrowed ſpeech taken for the Temple, the legall worſhip, and the Church of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> whereof the Temple was a ſeate and dwelling place, the ſhadow of heavenly things, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.5. and we know that the Church is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Kingdome of Heaven, in many places of Scripture, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.2. So that ſhake heaven, is to aboliſh the viſible Church, that were of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> or are now of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.41.43. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13.</note>For where God will ſhake the heaven (firſt of the Church) and the Earth (of unbelievers) they ſhall be aboliſhed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.27. but once more ſaith the Lord, will I ſhake the heaven. 1. Of the Church, and the Earth, 1. Vnbelievers, <hi>Ergo</hi> they ſhall be aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>By the Earth is meant in that place, men, corrupt unbelievers, as <hi>O Earth,</hi> heare the word of the Lord. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> 1. O men that are earth, of all Nations of the Earth, and all the Kingdomes of the Heathen, ſhall be ſhaken as <hi>Hagg.</hi> 2, 27. as well as the Churches, <hi>For behold ſaith the Lord I have begun to plague the City which my Name is called upon,</hi> and ſhould you eſcape, you ſhal ſurely drinke. <hi>Iere.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> So God will ſhake the heaven of the church of Chriſtians, and ſhould the Earth of Turkes and Heathens eſcape, they ſhall be overthrowne. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> To ſhake the earth therefore is to ſhake the corrupt unbelieving earthly people out of their places, as he ſhooke the <hi>Iewes</hi> heaven of the church, and the Earth of the heathen, becauſe they received not one baptiſme into Chriſts death, for remiſſion of ſinnes, but deſpiſed the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God againſt their owne ſoules, and to make a church, and therefore he ſhooke them downe <hi>Luke</hi> 7.30. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. <hi>Ro.</hi> 6.3. So that heaven you ſee is put for the Church, and the earth, for all corrupt unbelieving people, Therefore as God ſhooke the heaven, and the earth after Chriſts death, for their not receiving of him by baptiſme into his death, as <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.9.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. <hi>For every ſoule that will not heare that Prophet</hi> (1. To be baptiſed in his Name, if he have not, for the remiſſion of ſinnes, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38.) <hi>Shall be deſtroyed among the people,</hi> and they were deſtroyed from being the church and people of God, and became the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Sathan. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9. God rejected the old church of the heaven of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and ſet up a new heaven of the Church of the Gentiles, that did receive Chriſt by baptiſme, and faith, as the 3000. did, and the Churches of all Nations. So when God ſhall have mercy upon the forlorne forſaken Nation, and make them partakers of ſalvation by Chriſt, he ſhall ſhake the former heaven of the corrupt, Idolatrous, dead, lukewarme churches of the Gentiles, becauſe they believe not one baptiſme into Chriſts death, for remiſſion of ſinnes, as <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38.22.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. and make the dignity and honour of the holy City of the New Ieruſalem, of <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to be ſo glorious, as a new heaven and a new earth. Hence I gather this Doctrine,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervati∣on. </seg>
               </label> That there ſhall be a new church of the new Jeruſalem upon earth, and this I prove by <hi>Eſay</hi> 65.17. <hi>For behold I am about to create, new heavens, and a new Earth,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, I will inſtitute a more pure church, faith and worſhip in ſpirit and in truth, and I will take unto me a new people in the Aſſemblies, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I will be worſhipped, and honoured, and I will make a new Earth of new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>for if any man be in Chriſt he is a new creature,</hi> 2 Cor 5.17. <hi>For old things are paſſed away behold all things are become new,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. which ſhall be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114500:3"/>
moſt plainely verified, when the old churches paſſe away, and the new Jeruſalem appeare, as <hi>Eſay</hi> 43.19. <hi>Behold I will doe a new thing in the Earth, now it ſhall ſpring forth,</hi> ſhall yee not know it, when may ſome ſay, <hi>Anſ. Rev.</hi> 21.5. <hi>Behold I make all things new, and he ſaid to me write, for theſe words are true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> 1. There ſhall be a new heaven and a new Earth, a new church, and people, for he that ſat on the Throne, bad <hi>Iohn</hi> write it, and he hath given me a minde to know him that is true, and for to write of things that are true, for if it be true, as it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th Behold I make all things new, then that muſt be a new church, or elſe al things ſhall not be new for as the new heaven and the new earth, which I will make, ſhall remaine before me ſaith the Lord, compare the place with this, and you ſhall finde it agree with this, and cannot agree to the former churches of <hi>Epheſus Smyrna, Pergamus, Thyatira, Sardis, Phyladelphia, Laodicea,</hi> for they ſhall paſſe away, but the church of new Jeruſalem ſhall remaine, <hi>For to him that overcometh in the Churches, I will make him a pillar in the Temple of my God, and ſhall goe no more out, and write upon him the Name of the new Ieruſalem,</hi> that cometh downe from my God out of heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.12. but when is this to be? when the lukewarme An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell that is neither cold nor hot is ſpued out of Chriſts mouth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.16.</note> in <hi>Laodicea</hi> of England this new Church is to appeare, but now the lukewarme Angels are ſpued out. <hi>Ergo.</hi> It is now to appeare, I could prove this by many Arguments but I ſet downe but five.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> The cauſes why the Churches of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall depart, and all their Sees of iuriſdiction and the new Ieruſalem appeare,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> For if there ſhall be an holy City of new Ieruſalem come downe from God out of Heaven, trimmed as a Bride, for her Bridegroome, then there muſt be a new Church upon Earth, for by new Ieruſalem, is meant the Church of God. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the holy City, the new Ieruſalem come downe from God out of heaven. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.2. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go.</hi> there muſt be a new Church upon earth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> That City which ſhall be foure ſquare and, ſhall be meaſured by an Angell a man, with a golden reed, 12000. Furlongs, muſt needs be upon Earth, for there is neither ſquares nor furlongs, nor reedes, nor men meaſurers of any thing there, for all was prepared for thee, before the foundation of the world, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25, 34. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But the Church of the new Ieruſalem, ſhall lye foure ſquare, and be meaſured by an Angell, a man, with a golden reed, 12000. Furlongs, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Ergo</hi> it muſt needs be upon earth for there is no ſquares, reeds, or Furlongs, or men meaſurers, in actuall glory.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> That City which ſhall have twelve gates, and twelve Angels, and the Names of the Tribes of Iſrael, 3. On the Eaſt, 3. On the North, 3. On the South, 3. On the Weſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> muſt needes be meant of a Church or City upon Earth, for there is no Eaſt nor Weſt, North, nor South, in actuall glory, or but twelve gates, or but twelve Angels, for there is more then twelve Legions of Angels there, but the Church of the new Jeruſalem, ſhall have twelve gates, and twelve Angels, and the names of the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 3. to the Eaſt, 3. to the North, 3. on the South, 3. on the Weſt, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.13. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> it muſt needs be a City, or Church upon earth, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſhewes it muſt be a Church of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> baptized and made new creatures, for the <hi>Gentiles</hi> have not twelve Tribes, and if there be any gates in heaven, they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t made long before their were any tribes of <hi>Iſrael. v.</hi> 12.13.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> That City which ſhall have a Wall, with twelve foundations, and in them the Names of the Lambs twelve Apoſtles, muſt be new Church upon earth build on the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114500:4"/>
doctrine of the twelve Apoſtles, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> for the Apoſtles can be no foundation of a Wall of a City in heaven, for it was made before there were Apoſtles, before the foundation of the world. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. <hi>But the new Ieruſalem ſhall have a Wall, with twelve foundations, and in them the names of the lambe twelve Apoſtles,</hi> as <hi>v.</hi> 14. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo.</hi> It muſt be a new Church upon Earth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>5</label> That City which ſhall have the Nations that are ſaved, to walke in the light of it, and the Kings of the Earth, to bring their glory and honour to it, muſt be a new Church upon Earth. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> For the people that are ſaved, they ſhall not need to walke in hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en, for they ſhall be as the Angels of God in heaven, which flie or paſſe in an inconceivable time, as the body of Chriſt to heaven, and the things of the Earth ſhall bring no honour or glory to heaven, for heaven ſhall give glory and honour to them. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But the Church of the new Jeruſalem shall be ſuch wherein the Nations that are ſaved, shall walke in the light of it, and the Kings of the Land shall bring their honour &amp; glory to it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24 (i. e. they shall account it their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glory to be Citizens of new Ieruſalem, and bring their ſubjects to it.) <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> it muſt be a new Church upon Earth. I could give more reaſons if theſe be not ſufficient.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
               </label> Shall there be a new Church upon earth, Then ſay the <hi>Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, Seperatiſts, Familiſts, Adamites, Millenaries, Antitrinitarians, Arminians, Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Sectaries, and Selectaries.</hi> (all which are commonly notable Phariſes, and by a ſuperabundance of religion,<note place="margin">Which have no aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of ſalvation, for out of the church is no ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nor aſſurance of it.</note> like ſcabs and warts, by the abundance of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, grow out of the body of man, ſo by the humours of their braine, doe theſe grow out of the Church, and ſeperate from it.) then we will goe make a New Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> You are greatly deceived not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God, for firſt it muſt come downe from heaven from my God, <hi>Ergo,</hi> man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not build it. 2. That which is of God, ſhall ſtand, for God is the builder and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of that City. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. But the worke or Church that is of man, shall come to naught, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. Thirdly, The Church of new Ieruſalem, muſt be built 12000. Furlongs in length, breadth and height you cannot build none ſo great. Fourthly, The New Church muſt be built of pure gold, like unto cleare glaſſe, but you have got none of that to build with, for the gold growes, in the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> Rev. 3.18. Which wee have forſaken. Fifthly, You have no Iaſper ſtone for your wall, nor fine linnin which is bright and pure, the juſtifications of the Saints, to trime your Church with, but your Bride hath got a menſtruous garment of mans righteouſneſſe, that ſayes ſtand a part I am holier then thou, or I will ſtand a part, and ſeparate from you, thus you have neither gold, nor precious ſtones, nor white raiment to trime your Church, but your builders are all divided, and your language confounded, before you begin you shall build a Babel for the New Church comes from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the builder and founder of it is God, and the government of it muſt come from God, before we shall have one, as I tould you, three yeares ſince in my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Booke of the bloud of the Lambe, but you believed it not, but thought you should have had a better Reformation, and government before this time, but are deceived, and not I. It followeth for the firſt Heaven, and the firſt Earth, are paſſed away.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
               </label> What shall the other Churches then of the Gentiles faile &amp; come to decay, for hath heaven noteth out the Church, as you have proved? <hi>Anſwer.</hi> We need not trouble
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114500:4"/>
our ſelves to prove it, for the diviſions of all Churches and people againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves doe ſhew it, for they are ſending one another to hell as faſt as they can, by ſword, perſecution, hatred, envy and malice; diſſention, hereſies, ſects and ſchiſmes and drunkenneſſe, and covetouſneſs, they make poſt haſt to hell-ward. For where the heaven of a Church is divided againſt itſelfe, it cannot continue, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. But the Church of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and of <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and of <hi>Engliſh,</hi> are heaven of Churches that are divided againſt themſelves. <hi>Ergo,</hi> they cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, they are heavens that are waxed olde, <hi>as a garment and as a veſture ſhall hee change them</hi> The Pope and all his Idolaters, and his ceremonies, the dead faith conſubſtantiated <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and the luke-warme faith of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> ſhall be ſpewed out of Chriſts mouth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.10. And the Heretickes, Seperators from the Church, with the profane unbelievers, ſhall be rooted out. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>For every plant which my heavenly Father planted not ſhall be rooted out,</hi> Matth. 15.15. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> But they which will not buy gold, white raiment, and eye-ſalve, are plants which my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father hath not planted. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo, they ſhall be rooted out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> As touching the reformed Churches; What, ſhall the receiving of the Jewes bee the eſtranging of the Gentiles from being Churches? as if caſting away the Church of the Jewes was the reconcilement of the world. i. e. Of the Churches of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.15. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is very plaine, becauſe the Apoſtle certifieth us in that place, that there is a certaine fulneſſe of the Gentiles to be made up, which is to be at the calling of the Jewes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. for if <hi>John</hi> ſaw the former heaven and the former earth departed, then you muſt appoint them a time to paſſe away in. And when the luke-warme Angels of <hi>Laodicea</hi> is ſpewed out of Chriſts mouth, <hi>i. e.</hi> which is the laſt Church of the Gentiles, they ſhall paſſe away for being any more chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; for the former heaven are the Churches of the Gentiles which he ſaw depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Ergo,</hi> they ſhall paſſe away.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> The Gentiles which are ſaved ſhall walke in the light of the new <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Then they ſhall leave the candle-lights of the Churches of the Gentiles (which are called Candleſticks, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. they were of,  and walke in the light of the new Church that ſhall be on earth, and be one with them. <hi>For bleſſed is he that doth his commandements, that his right way may be in the tree of life, that bee may enter in through the gates of the City,</hi> Rev. 22.14.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> And the Kings of the Earth ſhall bring their glory and honour to that Church of the new <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>An.</hi> This makes againſt you alſo: for if they doe ſo, then they ſhall leave to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their olde Churches, and their governments, and ſhall honour the holy City, to be the only true Church. And as we have had Kings of <hi>England,</hi> that above all the Kings in Chriſtendom have been Kings of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> So wee shall have againe Kings of <hi>England,</hi> that shall be Kings of the Church of new <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Let our King hearken to this, <hi>for the Kings of the earth ſhall bring their honour and glory both,</hi> verſ. 14. The cauſes why the Churches of the Gentiles shall depart, and their Sees and the Church of new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> appeare.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> It ſeemes there ſhall be a flouriſhing Church of the Gentiles, when the Jewes ſhal be called. For ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> If the caſting away of the Jewes were the riches of the Gentiles, or the reconciliation of the world, what ſhall their aſſuming be life from the dead? I anſwer, it is true; for the <hi>Lutherans</hi> that eſcape the bloudy Civill warr, and turne, ſhall ariſe out of the dead faith, and the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114500:5"/>
out of the luke-warme faith, to walke in the golden ſtreet of the lovely faith of the merits of Chriſts death in one baptiſme for the remiſſion of ſins, as the 3000. did, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. and ſo Papiſts and Heathens ſhall ariſe out of their idolatrous and ſuperſtitious faith, and embrace the true faith of the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of the Jews and Gentiles, <hi>v</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>Out of which words we gather, that the fulneſſe of the Gentiles is not a certaine end of their believing at the calling of the Jewes, as if faith ſhould utterly fall away among the Gentiles; as nothing can be powred more into a full veſſell: but that there ſhall be a more plentifull comming in of all the Nations of the Earth, leaving their olde, dead, luke-warm and Idolatrous Churches, and ſhall obey the true faith of the Church of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.9. <hi>The Lord ſhall be King over all the earth in that day, there ſhall be one Lord, (and one faith, and one baptiſme</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Epheſ. 4.5. whereas now wee have many) <hi>and his Name ſhall be one,</hi> i.e. <hi>and the name of his Church ſhall be one, new</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12. God will write it on them, <hi>and one Shepheard, and one ſheepe-fold,</hi> John 10.16. and <hi>Iſa</hi> 25.7, 8. <hi>And the Lord ſhall deſtroy in this mountaine the covering that covereth all people, and the vaile that is ſpread upon all,</hi> i. e. the vail of ignorance of their baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me into Chriſts death for the remiſſion of ſinnes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. For few have this vaile of infidelity removed, <hi>and the Lord ſhall wipe all away all teares from their faces, and he will take away the rebuke of his people out of the earth,</hi> i. e. at the calling of the Jewes, as <hi>Pſalm</hi> 77.9, 10, 11. <hi>For the Kings of</hi> Tarſhiſh <hi>and of the Iſles ſhall bring preſents,</hi> whereof the King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> is a King of the Iſles, <hi>Ergo,</hi> he that is or ſhall be King, ſhall bring gifts to the new <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Sheba</hi> and <hi>Saba</hi> ſhall bring gifts. Yea all Kings ſhall worſhip, all Nations ſhall ſerve him. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the King of <hi>England,</hi> and the Nation of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or elſe all ſhall not. For ſuch a contradiction cannot be true, that all ſhould ſerve him, and ſome ſhould not; that all Kings ſhould ſerve, and all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though it be not ſaid every particular man of every Nation, for many ſhal be caſt into the lake, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. &amp; 27. But all the Kings of the Earth ſhall be Citizens of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for none ſhall be counted a true King, except hee embrace the faith of the new <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> that as heretofore the Kings of the Earth have counted it their honour to be Citizens of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to have brought honour to <hi>Rome,</hi> and crowned there, ſo they ſhall count it their honour and glory to be Citizens of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and bring their Subjects to it. The King would have no Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, and the Parliament will have no Epiſcopacy, and the <hi>Independents</hi> will have none of both. You may heave and ſhove, and plot by policy to ſet up a govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but you ſhall ſet up none, as I have told you three yeares ſince, untill the Church of new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> appeare, that ſhall have a government from heaven: for all your labour will be but to pull downe each other, for you are divided, that your houſe cannot ſtand, much leſſe ſet up a houſe or government in ſuch a diviſion, and you will ſay hereafter I could ſee further into a milſtone then you.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> In this common reſort therefore of the Nations, how ſhall the firſt heaven, i. e. the Church among the Gentiles paſſe away? muſt we diſtinguiſh the Nations thus? ſome are Heathens, and ſome Chriſtians, ſhall there be an acceſſe made of thoſe as the propheſies declare, and doe it ſignifie a departure and revolt of theſe?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The viſion which theſe words declare, point at ſome ſuch matter; for it is ſaid the firſt heaven parted away, for what other heaven is there amongſt men, then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:114500:5"/>
Church amongſt us Chriſtians; for the church is called heaven, as in many places of Scripture, as in page 1. The promiſe made to <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> of the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that it ſhould be a pillar in the Temple of God, never to be caſt out, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12. It was, if they held faſt that faith that they had, and did not let any man take their crown from them, i.e. the crowne of their baptiſme,<note place="margin">The gold of heaven.</note> which is made of the pure gold of heaven, the merits of Chriſts death in one baptiſme for remiſſion of ſinnes, which that church in many places have loſt, by taking a ſecond baptiſme for no remiſſion, but for diſcipline, and therefore ſhall have a grievous deſtruction, as 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. their peace with <hi>Spaine</hi> which procures it, for whilſt they were at war with <hi>Spaine,</hi> their Sectaries and Hereticks all held together againſt the common enemie: but now they will all fall apieces as <hi>England</hi> doth, and the ſword deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> One asketh this queſtion, to what end was this promiſed to <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> as a proper and peculiar benefit, if all the reſt enjoy the ſame together with her?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, it belongs to her no more then it doth to all the reſt,  <hi>for what I ſay to you</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I ſay to all,</hi> Mark. 13. ſo what I ſay to one Church, I ſay to all; for the <hi>Lutherans</hi> few names, and the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that overcome, <hi>and bold faſt that they have, and let no man take away their Crown of baptiſme,</hi> ſhall be made a pillar of the Temple, and have the name of the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> written upon them as well as the <hi>Philadelphians. For all the promiſes are yea and Amen to them that believe and are baptized,</hi> as well as to them. <hi>For hee that believeth, and is baptized into Chriſts death for the remiſſion of ſins, ſhall be ſaved:</hi> and the <hi>Philadelphians</hi> ſhall be no more, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. And this appeares to be ſo by the ſaying; <hi>Let him that hath an eare heare what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches,</hi> not to the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Now out of theſe words thus diſcuſſed, I gather, that the former heaven, or the Churches of the Gentiles that are now viſible, ſhall depart and paſſe away, as by many reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Re. </seg>1</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> For where there is an unfruitfull fig-tree that cumbereth the ground, the deſtiny of it, when it hath been digged and dunged, and yet bringeth forth ill fruite, it is to be hewne downe, that another may be planted as the Jewes were. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But the viſible Churches of the Gentiles have been unfruitfull fig-trees, that have been digged and dunged, and yet have brought forth ill fruit, as idolatrous, dead, and luke-warme fruit, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. &amp; 3. ch. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> their deſtiny is to be cut downe,<note place="margin">Con.</note> that another may be planted.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Re. </seg>2</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> For where the Husbandmen looke ill to the Vine-yard that was let out to them, there it ſhall be taken away, and let out to others, as the Church of the Jewes was to the Gentiles, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.41. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.6. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But the churches of the Gentiles are Vineyards that have been let out to Husbandmen. i.e. Angels, that have looked ill to them. For by the Vineyard let out to Husbandmen, is meant the Church, as the parable declares, and the Husbandmen were the high Prieſts, Scribes and Phariſes, of the Jewes, and the Idolatrous, dead, or luke-warme Biſhops or Paſtors of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <hi>Rev.</hi> ch. 2. &amp; 3. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> the churches of the Gentiles are Vineyards, that ſhall be taken away from them, and let out to others. i.e. to the Jewes. <hi>For the Kingdome of heaven ſhall be taken away from you</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) and let out to others. i.e. the Church, which is not only given to the Jewes, but alſo to the Gentiles, that have abuſed the Church as they. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Re. </seg>3</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> For where Chriſts Miniſters are beaten and ſtoned and killed, there Chriſt ſaith <hi>he will deſtroy thoſe murtherers, and burne up their City.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But in the Churches of the Gentiles, as of <hi>Rome, France, Germany,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ma. Mi.</note> of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114500:6"/>
               <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and of <hi>England,</hi> his Miniſters have been killed, beaten, and abuſed with ſundry perſecutions, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> he will deſtroy thoſe murtherers, and burne up their city, you ſee a ſhrewd argument, why <hi>Rome, Paris,</hi> and many cities of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> should be burned.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Re. </seg>4</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> For where the Church hath been abuſed, and evill intreated a long time, she will bethinke her ſelfe of truſſing up her ſtuffe, and forſake them, and goe to another people, as the church of the olde world forſooke them, and got into the Arke, and the church of the Jewes forſooke them, and went to the Gentiles, and the Church of Papiſts forſooke them, and went to the <hi>Lutherans, Calviniſts</hi> and <hi>Engliſh.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But the Church have been abuſed and evill entreated a longtime of the Gentiles. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſhee will forſake them and goe to another people.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Re. </seg>5</label> Now thoſe heavens <hi>that waxe olde as a garment, and as a veſture ſhall hee change them, and they ſhall be changed, ſhall paſſe away, becauſe they are impure in his eyes,</hi> Job 15.15. Now this cannot be ſo properly meant of the ſtarry heavens as of the Churches; for how should they be impure in Gods eyes, which never ſinned; neither can any shew, that God ever imputed any ſin to them, or curſe, as to the Earth for <hi>Adams</hi> ſake; for they are as God have made them, and they all continue by his appointment.</p>
            <p>But the Church of the old World waxed olde, and the church of the Jewes, and the heaven of Papiſts, <hi>Lutherans, Calviniſts</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> are waxed olde, becauſe they are impure in his eyes, for he ſaith <hi>he hath ſome things againſt them. Ergo,</hi> they ſhall paſſe away. For the heaven of the viſible Churches of <hi>England, Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> are not only uncleane at this day in a ſmall manner. (Now miſtake mee not, to thinke that I meane the juſtified people of God of all theſe 3. churches, for I believe they are cleane every whit.</p>
            <p>The cauſes why the viſible Churches shall depart, and the Church of new <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> appeare perfectly righteous, and holy without ſpot before the Throne of God. But of the outward viſible Church, and all ſeparate Synagogues, that call themſelves churches of Hereticks, Sectaries, and Schiſmaticks, which I count farre worſe then the ſeven churches, becauſe Chriſt wrote to theſe by name, and hath his Elect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe, but he writes not to the other; and if the Fathers ſay true, hee hath not God for his Father, that hath not the church for his Mother; and the Scripture ſaith, <hi>(God added to the Church ſuch as ſhould be ſaved.)</hi> yet I ſay the viſible church is uncleane, not in a ſmall manner, though it be called by ſo glorious a name, as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which is ſpoken in reſpect of the darke dungeon of hell, of the Jewes, Turkes, Heathens, and Papiſts, then for any heavenly cleareneſſe of the glory of God in gold of the merits of Chriſts death, in one baptiſme, for a perfect remiſſion of ſinnes, or for the glory of the Lambs white rayment, juſtification for an everlaſting righteouſneſs, Shew me a church on Earth that is found in the faith of theſe three, gold, white rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and eye-ſalve, <hi>&amp; Phillida ſolus habebis,</hi> let her be thy Love.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Re. </seg>6</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> For the Church is defiled with a falſe faith, or reigning ſinne, there the church is uncleane,  and shall therefore be removed. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But all the churches of the Gentiles are defiled with a falſe faith, or reigning ſinne, for why should Chriſt ſay elſe, <hi>hee hath ſome things againſt them, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
                  </label> Ergo,</hi> they are uncleane in Gods ſight, and shall therefore be removed. For what foote ſteps of one baptiſme for remiſſion of ſinnes, and of a white raiment, Juſtification doe remaine? For doe not all viſible Churches hold they muſt goe knocke at heaven gates every day to get a pardon for their ſins, as if
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114500:6"/>
they were not forgiven, as <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. And to wipe off olde ſcores, as if God did ſcore up ſinnes every day, till they pray; and they muſt goe get God to caſt all their ſins into the bottome of the Sea, as if they were not caſt into the bottom of the red Sea of Chriſts bloud already, <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.19. in baptiſme into Chriſts death, <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16. And confeſſe God is angry with them for their ſinnes, and ſee ſinne in them, and puniſh them for the ſame: is not this to ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e an angry God? as all heathens, Turkes and Jewes doe, and not a reconciled Father, which if it were to get remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſins to the conſcience, I would not fault it but to the perſon, as if that were not reconciled: it croſſeth <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.21. And the article of the Creed. i. e. I believe the remiſſion of ſinnes: as for the <hi>Lutherans</hi> of <hi>Sardis,</hi> they are in the dead faith, and their works not perfect before God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1.2. Their dead workes of hatred to the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> declare their dead faith: And as for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> luke-warme <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceans,</hi> they hold as the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> did at his death, he ſaid he hoped God would forgive him his ſinnes. Now ſuch as the faith of the great Angel was, ſuch is the faith of moſt people of the Church. What heathen, Jew, Turke, Papiſt, or Devill, had not as good a faith as this, to ſay I hope God is mercifull, and will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give me my ſinnes; he might goe to Purgatory (if there were one) for all this faith. The decay in knowledg of one baptiſme for remiſſion of ſins, and in the Articles of the Creed, they doe not preach or pray in this faith, that we have redemption, as <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.14. <hi>And that our ſinnes are forgiven us for his names ſake,</hi> 1 John 2.12. It is an hard thing to finde a Miniſter, that hath aſſurance of ſalvation, or that can tell where he had remiſſion of ſins,; for few of them believe they were made in their baptiſme members of Chriſt, children of God, and Inheritors of the Kingdome of heaven, or believe, that in the white raiment, they are ſo cloathed, that God beholds no ſhame of nakedneſſe of ſin in them. And ſeeing this faith is loſt, what new Errours ſpring up every day, and broached in many places, olde ones are called backe from hell by hereticks, <hi>Anabaptiſts, Papiſts, Familiſts, Adamites, Arminians, Socinians, Browniſts, Seperatiſts,</hi> all the profeſſion of unity &amp; ſpirituall peace turned to blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and civill Warre in all the churches in <hi>Chriſtendome.</hi> Theſe are fearefull ſignes, and evident Prognoſtications, that the Churches are departing.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Re. </seg>7</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> For where the churches are fallen from the trueth, it is an argument the church ſhall depart from them. For thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Remember from whence thou art fallen,</hi> Rev. 3.5. <hi>Or elſe I will remove the Candleſticke out of his place.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But all the viſible churches are fallen from the truth, as <hi>Papiſts</hi> to idolatry, <hi>Lutherans</hi> to a dead faith and workes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Re.</hi> 3.1.2.</note> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> to a luke-warme faith &amp; reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſin, uſury or drunkenneſſe; for it was never known that the truth did continue in any one church above 100. years, but they fell from it, as the homily of our church of the perill of Idolatry. 3. p. c. it is 100. yeares ſince <hi>England</hi> received the truth, and therefore the time is come by their owne confeſſion, that they should fall from it. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is an argument the church ſhould be removed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Re. </seg>8</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> Every kingdome, city or houſe divided againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand, but come to nought, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But all the former churches of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> are king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, cities or houſes divided againſt themſelves, witneſſe the <hi>Papiſts, Lutherans, Calviniſts,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh.</hi> You ſee what fighting and writing there is now one againſt another. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> they cannot ſtand, but come to nought.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Re. </seg>9</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> For where the Sunne ariſeth, the light of the candle muſt depart, for the light of the Churches of the Gentiles, was but as candles, for the churches were but golden
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114500:7"/>
Candleſticks, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But the light of the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is as the light of the Sunne, that shall never goe downe, and their light of the Sunne shall be 7. fold, and as the light of ſeven days. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> the light of the churches of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> muſt vanish, becauſe their light is but as candles.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Some ſay it is not ſaid the former heaven and the former earth went away, but that they departed, as if theſe words did not reſpect the churches of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> at all, but the legall worship of the Jewes onely. For a man may call that the firſt heaven by right, as which was inſtituted by <hi>God</hi> himſelfe in the beginning of the World, a little time after the floud. But the Chriſtian people among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> was neither the firſt heaven, neither were their Ordinances which are obſerved of them, the firſt Ordinances that were delivered from heaven unto the church, ſo that ſome would have it taken in this manner, as if it were ſaid, although this people of the Jewes did thirſt after their olde rights and worſhip all this while of their rejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and did make their bragges of it, that the time would come when they should have power given them one day to exerciſe their former worſhip freely, after their old manner, which is the thing they have boaſted of till this day. Yet in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of the Jewes, they shall ſo wholly frame and apply themſelves to the will of God, that they shall willingly renounce their ancient cuſtomes, uſed in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, which they shall then acknowledge to have had their end in Chriſt, and by this meanes they shall make it plaine to all men, that the firſt heaven and the firſt earth which they hoped to ſee againe, was departed, was paſt for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> The Pope that would have Saint <hi>Peters</hi> chair to remain to the end of the world, and all Sectaries that would have their church way as they falſely call it, and all other that are loth their churches should depart, like this interpretation beſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> But this is falſe to this place of Scripture. For the firſt heaven cannot be meant of the Churches of the ancient Jewes, but of the churches of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> theſe are my Reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, becauſe the olde church of the Iewes was not called by the name of heaven, for <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt and Chriſt were the firſt that preached the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to be at hand, therefore the firſt heaven muſt belong to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> for the laſt ſhall be firſt, and the firſt ſhall be laſt; <hi>i. e.</hi> the laſt Church of the Gentiles shal be the firſt heaven, and the firſt church of the Jewes shall be the laſt new heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, If this should be expounded of of the Jewes church, then there should have been no heaven of a church among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ever ſince Chriſts time. But onely the firſt heaven hath been among the Jewes all this while, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> have had none in the 7. churches, although Chriſt wrote to them, yet they were no heaven or church; too abſurd.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, this muſt be underſtood of the church of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Jewes</hi> were broken off, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.15.24. i. e. from being a church, and the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> graffed in, and made an heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, for the Kingdome of heaven which was offered to them, and preached among them: but they put it away from them, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46. The Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven was taken away from them, and given to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> above 1600. yeares, and therefore the <hi>Jewes</hi> could not be the firſt heaven, becauſe they did not receive it when it was offered, but deſpiſed the counſell of God, &amp; therefore if the firſt king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven was given to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> then the firſt heaven belongs to them. For as Chriſt came to his owne, but his owne received him not: ſo the kingdome of heaven was preached to them, but they received it not.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114500:7"/>The cauſes why the Churches of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall depart and the Church of New Ieruſalem appeare.</p>
            <p>Note Fiftly, This cannot be meant of the <hi>Iewes</hi> that they are now the firſt heaven becauſe as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of Oxen, doth God take care for Oxen. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.9. So doth God take care for <hi>Iewes,</hi> that are made the Synagogue of Sathan. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9. For that which is ſo is not an heaven. Therefore the firſt heaven that paſſed away is to be underſtood of the Church of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> for the true Church of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> was the Kingdome of Heaven <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; Matth.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>Now the cauſes why the firſt heaven of the Churches of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> depart are theſe.<note place="margin">Cauſes why the Churches of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt the church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> was a famous heaven, watered with the bloud of the Martyrs, in the 10. perſecutions, of the primative Church, built upon the bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme into Chriſts death, for remiſſion of ſinnes, and faith in the ſame as <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. <hi>Act.</hi> 8. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. <hi>Act.</hi> 16. and <hi>Act.</hi> 22.16. and on the love of God ſhewed in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſame as <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. <hi>But becauſe they forſooke their firſt love of Chriſt.</hi> 1. e. Their firſt Baptiſme, wherein the firſt love of Chriſt was ſhewed to take a ſecond Baptiſme, which they did by the counſell of the <hi>Hereticks, Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> that all that were baptized by <hi>Hereticks,</hi> muſt be baptized a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and becauſe they did not know, who was baptized by Orthodox men, they rebaptized the people, which was iniquity of ſo high a nature, a ſinne againſt the worke of the Holy Ghoſt, that Chriſt removed the Candleſtick of the church out of that place, by the Turke, and ſo that heaven is departed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> though a famous rich conquering &amp; reigning Church, in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, for it was rich as the Lord ſaid. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9. i. e. In the faith of one Baptiſme for remiſſion of ſinnes, as the Article of the <hi>Niceen</hi> Creed declares, but in time they followed after <hi>Epheſus,</hi> as all the other churches of <hi>Greece,</hi> they forſooke the truth of one Baptiſme, the firſt love of God declared. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. (as many now doe in theſe dayes) by forſaking their firſt Baptiſme into Chriſts death for remiſſion of ſinnes, for it was never knowne that the truth did continue in one place, above an hundred yeares, but they forſooke it, or fell from it into ſome falſe faith, or reigning ſinne. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> 3. The church of <hi>Pergamus.</hi> 1. e. Of old <hi>Rome</hi> is departed from being a church, becauſe they maintained the doctrine of <hi>Balaam.</hi> i. e. Idolatry and fornication, and the Doctrine of the <hi>Nicholaitans,</hi> by Stewes &amp; whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> Therefore Chriſt fought againſt them, with the ſword out of his mouth, and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> they are departed from being true church for where God fights againſt a church, for ſinne by the ſword out of his mouth, it muſt depart from being a true church but the church of <hi>Pergamus</hi> was ſuch, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Ergo.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, The church of <hi>Thiatira,</hi> of new <hi>Rome.</hi> is departed from being a true church, becauſe ſhe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the woman <hi>Iezabel</hi> amongſt them, which was a Witch, a whore, and a murdereſſe, and though God hath given her ſpace, yea the longeſt ſpace to repent of any other, yet ſhe repented not of her witchcraft, in bewitching men to Idolatry. not of her whoredome and abomination, nor of her murdering the Saints, for the ſcarled coloured Whore is drunke with the bloud of the Martyrs. And therefore Chriſt hath made her the Synagogue of Sathan. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.9. becauſe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Iewes</hi> or a catholique church, and are not, becauſe they have had time to repent and did not, they ſhall be deſtroyed. They are divided againſt themſelves, <hi>France</hi> againſt <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> againſt it ſelfe, it muſt downe. Now if any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114500:8"/>
will account the Martyrs, and true believers that lived for 200. yeares before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that ſuffered the manners of the <hi>Iezabel</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> amongſt them, that ſhould have been put away out of the church as <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> and England did, I account it the truth, but that which is ſpoken to <hi>Iezabel,</hi> is ſpoken to <hi>Rome,</hi> as their ſinnes declare,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The church of <hi>Sardis</hi> of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> is departing becauſe they are in the dead faith, which brought forth dead workes, that were not perfect before God. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1.2. and dead in love to the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and in love one to another, their faith of conſubſtantiation is a dead faith, that believe not their workes are perfect before God, by juſtification, neither can they believe ſo that live in hatred and perſecution of their brethren the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> that church is divided againſt it ſelfe, thus the <hi>Sweeds</hi> and <hi>Danes</hi> both <hi>Lutherans,</hi> were at Warre one with another lately, which have shot downe the one ſide of their church, from within, and a <hi>Papiſt</hi> the Emperour, and a <hi>Calviniſt</hi> is undermining the other ſide, for both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> fight againſt the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and they fight one with another, truly if one ſtone of a church should fight againſt another, could it ſtand, no, it muſt fall. Sixtly, The <hi>Phyladel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phian</hi> church of the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> is paſſing away, becauſe they have not held faſt that they had, for they had the true faith, and one baptiſme into Chriſts death for remiſſions of ſinne, taught by <hi>Calvin,</hi> and that doctrine eſtablished amongſt them, but many of them have not held faſt that they had, but have let the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> take <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> their crowne, for the crowne of a chriſtian is his baptiſme, for therein are all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect crowned,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.6.5 10.</note> with the crowne of pure gold, of the merits of Chriſts death, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinne, and made Kings and Prieſts to God their father, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.9. for as no man is a King, before he be crowned, ſo no man is a King and Prieſt to God, till he be baptized, many of them have loſt this crowne, by turning <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> a <hi>Lutheran,</hi> and an <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> are pulling downe the one ſide of their church, and a Sectary and a Drunkard are cutting and beating downe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, therefore it cannot ſtand, for Anababtiſme and drunkenneſſe, will deſtroy any church, whereſoever they grow, witneſſe the churches of <hi>Greece,</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> and many places in <hi>Iermany,</hi> for Hereſie is like Ivie, that kills an Oake by growing over it, and then men cut downe Oake and Ivie too, and ſo where Hereſie is ſuffered to grow in a church, it kills the church by overgrowing it, &amp; then God will deſtroy the church, and hereſie too, as shall be ſeene by the church of <hi>Calviniſts</hi> in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> it will be the deſtruction of the church of <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is paſſing away, for Chriſt ſpues the Luke-warme <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Angels, people that are lukewarme in the faith of their baptiſme, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, and in the white raiment, for England hath been divided againſt it ſelfe, and alſo <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> fights againſt them both, and divided againſt it ſelfe, alſo, The <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Cavalleers,</hi> have shot great holes in the one ſide of our church, to get an Epiſcopacy, but cannot, becauſe Chriſt ſpues it out of his mouth, an <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> ſtands as it were with a rope to pull downe the ſteeple, for he called it firſt a Steeple-houſe, and the <hi>Hereticks, Sectaries,</hi> and <hi>Selectaries,</hi> have pulled up all the foundations, as inſtance, Baptiſme, the Creed, the Lords prayer, the Decalog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, the Euchariſt, and Chriſtmas day, and the Euchariſt which hath bin as a foundation, of all the ſeven churches ever ſince the Apoſtles time, and ſo divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as I know not whether the King and Parliament will be reconciled ever, but the <hi>Preſbyters</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> will never, for their quarrell is begun, and will never
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114500:8"/>
end, for they ſcould, can ſuch a church ſtand, no, it muſt depart and paſſe away, for the people have ſo many frothings of religion in their braines, ſo many opinions and Hereſies that they will fall from being a church, to be a Babel, for as the <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> having a ſtrange phantaſie, would begin to build a tower, to reach to heaven, yet had no good materialls, but made brick inſtead of ſtone, and had ſlime inſtead of morter, this was mans invention, and it came to confuſion, for God confounded their language, &amp; ſcattered them, ſo many Hereticks &amp; Sectaries have got a conceipt in their crowne, to goe make a new church as a Tower to reach to heaven, for they would all goe to heaven, if they could goe their owne way, and they have concocted brick of the <hi>Browniſts</hi> braine, inſtead of doctrine, and they have diſcipline of phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie inſtead of morter, I am not againſt doctrine or diſcipline if they be from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but our new church-mungers have no good materialls of gold, white raiment, and eye-ſalve from heaven to build with, but the new Ieruſalem muſt be builded of pure gold, like cleare glaſſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.18 <hi>Of the gold of the merits of Chriſts death in regeneration, for remisſion of ſinnes, and of white raiment, to make the Bride trimme, and eye-ſalve of the Scriptures, that every thing may be done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the patterne ſhewed in the mount of Gods word.</hi> But doe you thinke blinde men are fit to build a church? you will ſay no, no more are all the <hi>Phariſes</hi> of our time, of all <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> whoſe froathing faith, or fancie, makes them boyle out of the church, which are blind leaders of the blinde for they leade many from Chriſts ordinance, for remiſſion of ſinnes, and blind in the aſſurance of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for they know not where they had remiſſion of ſinnes, but runne after every winde of Doctrine, and know not whether they shall be ſaved or be damned, or goe to heaven, or to hell, are you fit men, to build a church that are all ſo blinde that you cannot ſee ſpirituall things, ſo here ſayes one, wee will build this way, ſo there ſays a ſecond, we will build that way, ſo here ſayes a third, we will build another way, all of you ſay ſo, for you cannot ſee the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but are divided. <hi>Ergo.</hi> you cannot ſtand but come to nought. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>I proceed, of the overthrow, and departing of all corrupt Sees of Iuriſdiction.</p>
            <p>And there was no more ſea, or the ſea was extant no more.</p>
            <p>Now what is meant by the word ſea in this place? we muſt finde out this ridle, or enigmaticall metaphor, or elſe we shall faile to finde the new Jeruſalem, for it muſt not be founded on a ſea, for it commeth downe from heaven, from my God, but the ſeas are upon the Earth or the Earth upon them, for they make but one globe, as <hi>Coſmographie</hi> declares.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Now this cannot be underſtood of the materiall ſea, as if when the new Jeruſalem come downe from God out of heaven, there should be no more ſeas, for ships to ſaile in, for then how should the Kings of the Earth, bring their honour and glory to the new Jeruſalem, if there were no more ſeas, to ſaile on, which dwell beyond Sea, as <hi>v.</hi> 24. And how ſhould men goe downe to the Sea in ſhips and occupy their buſineſſe in great waters, if there were no more materiall ſea of waters, to faile in, wherefore as God made heaven and Earth, the Sea and all things therein, ſo long as the Earth ſhall remaine, there muſt be a materiall Sea, for God hath founded the Earth upon the Sea, and prepared it upon the flouds, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.2.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> This cannot properly be underſtood of the molten Braſen Sea, which Salomon made, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.25. <hi>For the Prieſts to waſh in,</hi> which ſhall not come into the new Jeruſalem, for that Sea of Braſſe, and that legall ceremony, or worſhip never
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114500:9"/>
came into the heaven of the church of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> therefore much leſſe ſhall it come into the holy city of the church of New Jeruſalem, which ſhall be moſt free from all legall cermonies, It is true that the <hi>Jewes</hi> have a proper Sea of their owne of Braſe, even till this day: which is moſt groſse, foule and darke, like to the rage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sea, that the wicked <hi>Jewes</hi> are like, which foameth out mire and dirt, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57.20. for they caſt out many forged doctrines, out of their owne braine, and legall deviſes, as touching a <hi>Mesſias</hi> to come, and a legall worſhip with ſacrifices, and righteouſnes by the law, and many other heads of corrupt doctrines which ſhall all depart from the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and ſhall never come into the heavenly Jeruſalem, neither was this in the church of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and therefore this Sea, here ſpoken of, muſt be ſuch an one, as was in the heaven of the churches of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, for the Sea here ſpoken of, is ſuch as the heaven was, as <hi>Meyer</hi> noteth, a metaphoricall heaven, and a metaphoricall ſea, and that is the ſea of the Iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of corrupt doctrine and diſcipline or government, which have been in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens of the churches of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in their ſeas, for what hath been more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for theſe many 100. yeares, then to talke of the holy Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> and for the church of <hi>England,</hi> to talke of the Sea of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Sea of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> Sea, as ſuch an impropriation, belongs to the Sea of <hi>Norwich,</hi> and ſuch a land to the Sea of <hi>Eli,</hi> and appeales were made to the Sea of Rome, and ſo were our appeales from one <hi>Biſhops</hi> Sea to another, but there ſhall be in the new heaven and in the new earth no more Sea, <hi>Ergo.</hi> there ſhall be no more Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or <hi>Yorke,</hi> and of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Lutherans</hi> or <hi>Calviniſts</hi> Sea, for all Seas of Iuriſdiction of government, of a corrupt diſcipline, and doctrine, ſhall now depart, and not enter into the holy Church of the new Jeruſalem, and that this is the meaning of the place, theſe are my Reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> For if the materiall heaven and earth ſhould paſſe away, the Sea muſt not remaine, for the Earth muſt be with the Sea, for it is founded upon it, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> ſo if the metaphoticall heaven, and Earth of the Church and people paſſe, ſo muſt their Sea (of Iuriſdiction) as text, but the firſt heaven and the firſt earth of the Churches ſhall paſſe away, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſo ſhall their ſeas of Iuriſdiction, for if a Church depart, then the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo muſt depart with it, and where the government of a church depart, the church commonly departs with it, for if a Kingdome depart or paſſe away muſt not the government depart with it? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> So if a church depart, that had the government of an Hierarchie of a <hi>popedome, Epiſcopacy</hi> for <hi>Preſbytery</hi> or <hi>Independent,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther government, for the Sea or diſcipline of a church cannot remaine, where the church depart, except you can make an accident remaine without a ſubject, for <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lato ſubjecto tollitur etiam accidens quta accidentis eſſe eſt ineſſe,</hi> for take away the ſubject and the accident of it is taken away, becauſe the being of an accident, is to be in the ſubject, as true reaſon, and the beſt <hi>Phyloſopher</hi> ſhewes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> For if we ſhall have an holy city of new Jeruſalem (i.e. a new church) come downe from heaven, trimmed as a Bride for her Bridegroome, then we muſt have a new government from heaven alſo (which muſt not be a Sea, for that was old, and not from heaven) or elſe it will not be very trimme long. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> But we ſhall have a church of New Jeruſalem come downe from heaven, trimmed as a Bride for her Bridgroome <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 21 2 <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo.</hi> we muſt have a new government, or elſe it will not be trimme long, for if it be true that God ſaith, <hi>behold I make all things new,</hi> then there can be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114500:9"/>
no more a Sea of <hi>Rome, Iuriſdiction,</hi> or of an <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> or <hi>Lutherans</hi> or <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> or of any other Church that ſhall paſſe away, for all theſe are old, and in that he ſaith a new covenant, he hath abrogated the old. <hi>He.</hi> 8.13. <hi>And that which is diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled and waxed old, is ready to vaniſh,</hi> ſo in that he ſaith, <hi>I make all things New,</hi> he hath abrogated the old churches, and ſeas. But it is true that God ſaith <hi>behold I make all things new, v.</hi> 5. <hi>Ergo,</hi> there can be no more Sea of <hi>Romes</hi> Iuriſdiction, or of an Epiſcopacy, or <hi>Lutherans, Calviniſts,</hi> or of another Church, that ſhall paſſe away for then all things ſhould not be become new.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>For every plant which my heavenly Father hath not planted, ſhall be rooted out. Matth.</hi> 15.13. But of the Sea of <hi>Romes</hi> Iuriſdiction, or diſcipline, or of the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy of England, or of the Sea of <hi>Lutherans,</hi> or <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> are plants which my heavenly Father hath not planted, if you ſay, they be, prove it if you can. But you cannot, for the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> was ſet up by the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the Sea of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> by the Proteſtants of England, and the government or Sea of the <hi>Lutherans</hi> by the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and the ſea of the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> by the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> now if the counſell of <hi>Gamaliel</hi> (approved on in Scripture) be true, then they muſt all come to nought. <hi>For every counſell or worke of man ſhall come to nought, but that which is of God ſhall ſtand, Acts</hi> 5.28. But the <hi>Popedome</hi> or Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> Sea of an Hierarchie of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Sea of <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> are counſels and workes of men, <hi>Ergo.</hi> they ſhall come to nought, but the church and government of the New Jeruſalem from God ſhall ſtand?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>6</label> Where a great voyce ſhall be heard out of heaven, ſaying, <hi>behold the Tabernacle of God is with men,</hi> there the church muſt be governed by the Oracles of Gods word, and not by a ſea of diſcipline of men, for the Oracle is in the Tabernacle, but in the New Jeruſalem there ſhall be a voyce out of heaven, ſaying, <hi>behold the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Lord is with men, Rev.</hi> 21.3. <hi>Ergo,</hi> there the Church muſt be governed by the Oracle of Gods word, and not by a Sea of diſcipline of men.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>7</label> For as fiſhes ſwimme and live in the Sea, ſo have Chriſtians ſailed, ſworne and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> Canterbury of <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> for they lived and walked in their Iuriſdiction government, diſcipline, for as the Sea have drowned many that have ſailed in it, ſo that Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and of <hi>Lutherans,</hi> &amp; <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> that have drowned many mens faiths in perdition, that ſailed in them, they are worthy to be no more, but the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> have drowned mens faith in Idolatry and purgatory, and the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Sea have drowned mens faith in confuſtantiation, &amp; dead faith and workes to the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> &amp; the Sea of our Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, and ſea of <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> have drowned many faiths in Lukewarmneſſe. <hi>Ergo,</hi> they are worthy to be no more, all theſe have drowned the faith of one baptiſme into Chriſts death, for remiſſion of ſinnes, for if this faith had ſwome in other Seas, what needed a <hi>Popes</hi> pardon a purgatory, a pilgrimage, conſubſtantiation, and workes not perfect before God, and a luke-warme faith without aſſurance of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>8</label> Thoſe Seas that have devoured abundance of ſubſtance of poore Chriſtians, and worthy to be no more. But the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> by purgatory, pardons, and pilgrimage and the ſeas of <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and of our Epiſcopacy, by licences, viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and courts, have devoured abundance of ſubſtance of poore Chriſtians, <hi>Ergo.</hi> they are worthy to be no more.</p>
            <p>Of the overthrow and departure of all the corrupt Seas of juriſdiction of the churches of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> For as the Sea compaſſeth the Land, and ſendeth Springs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114500:10"/>
or Rivers to all parts of the Land, to water it. So did the See of <hi>Rome</hi> and of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> and of the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe through all the parts of their Dominions, to water them with their Juriſdiction. For who was free in any Popiſh kingdome from Saint <hi>Peters</hi> pence, or Inquiſition Court, and Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, and power of the Pope, and who was freed in our Hierachy of the Epiſcopacy, from the high Commiſſion, Chauncellor, or Commiſſaries courts, Synods, Licences, or Parators, or freed in the <hi>Lutheran</hi> or <hi>Calviniſts</hi> Sees, from their Iuriſdiction and Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Now if the See of the Iuriſdiction of the Hierarchy of <hi>England</hi> be ſo departed that it can be no more; then the Sees of <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and of <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt follow, becauſe the Text ſaith, <hi>there ſhall be no more Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by the decree of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.16. and by the vote of Parliament, and the Oath of the people, the See of the Iuriſdiction of the Hierarchy of <hi>England</hi> is ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, that it can be no more. (For though King &amp; Parliament were agreed to ſet up an Epiſcopacy or Presbytery, but the Independents and Souldiers would never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it, for they rout them where they come) <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Sees of <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and of <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt follow, becauſe the Text ſaith, <hi>there ſhall be no more Sea. Judgement is begun at the houſe of God</hi> for their See, what shall become of the wicked See of <hi>Rome,</hi> even that which came upon olde <hi>Babylon,</hi> shall come upon the new <hi>Babylon</hi> of <hi>Rome. I will maintaine thy cauſe, and take vengeance for thee. I will dry up her Sea, and make her Springs dry for the people of Gods cauſe,</hi> Ier. 51.36. See O heaven rejoyce of her; for God will puniſh her to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged of her for your ſakes. For when a mighty Angel tooke up a great ſtone like a mil-ſtone, and caſt it into the Sea, ſaying, <hi>with ſuch violence ſhall that great thy of</hi> Babylon <hi>be caſt, and ſhall be found no more,</hi> Revel. 18.20, 21. If the great city of <hi>Babylon</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall be ſo caſt, what ſhall become of their See. He that believes not that <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Babylon</hi> that ſhall be deſtroyed, hath not ſo good a faith as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, who knows it is his habitation, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. and an hold of all foul ſpirits.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>10</label> For as the Sea uſeth to roare, preſaging ſtormes, which cauſeth Marriners to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 46.3. <hi>But he breaketh the raging of the Sea, when the waves thereof doe roare,</hi> Jer. 31.35. So when <hi>Martin Luther</hi> powred out his viall of Doctrine of free Iuſtification, how did the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Leo</hi> 10. roare againſt him with his exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable bull: but the Lord brake off part of that See, and it became a <hi>Lutheran, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinian,</hi> and <hi>Cantuarian</hi> See. And when the <hi>Lutheran</hi> See began to roare againſt the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> for conſubſtantiation, and perſecuted them, the Lord hath broken that See with one breaking after another. And when the See of <hi>Canterbury</hi> roared againſt the white-raiment chriſtians, and Non-conformiſts, ſuſpending them, and caſt them into priſon.<note place="margin">On wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Prin,</hi> Doctor <hi>Baſtwick.</hi>
               </note> And though a Shepheard got a piece of an eare out of the mouth of a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Amos</hi> 3. yet our Lion loved roſt cheekes and eares ſo well, that he left never a piece. Therefore the Lord hath broken the waves of the <hi>Cantuarian</hi> and Epiſcopal See when it roared, and that See ſhall be no more; and the See of <hi>Lutherans,</hi> that have roared at the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> ſhall be ſtilled, and the See of <hi>Rome</hi> that have roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and devoured the Martyrs of Jeſus shall be dryed up, and shall be burne, and be no more. For as Chriſt rebuked the materiall Sea when it roared againſt his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, he ſtilled it. So becauſe waves of the Metaphoricall ſeas that have roared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>11</label> his people, he will ſtill them, and they shall be no more; for as the raging troubled Sea caſteth out mire and dirt, <hi>Eſa</hi> 57.10. So have the troubled See of <hi>Rome Lutherans, Calviniſts,</hi> and of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> been like this troubled Sea, for when any
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114500:10"/>
troubled their ſeas, by writing or preaching the truth, they conceived it was againſt them, how have they foamed out mire and dirt of bloud and perſecution.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>11</label> Now if there shall no uncleane thing enter into the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> then no ſuch miry di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty Seas shall come into it, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ma. </seg>
               </label> as the See of <hi>Rome, Lutheran, Calvinian,</hi> or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopall See, for they are uncleane. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Mi. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>But there ſhall no uncleane thing enter into the new</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Con. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> no See of <hi>Rome, Lutheran, Calviniſt,</hi> or Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie shall come into it, for they are uncleane. We finde when the ſecond Angel pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out this Viall upon the ſea, and it became as the bloud of a dead man, and every living thing dyed in the Sea, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.3. That is, when <hi>Calvin</hi> had powred out his viall upon the ſea of Romes corrupt juriſdiction and Doctrine, for a <hi>Calvinian</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement. For <hi>Luther</hi> a former Angel had poured out his viall of Doctrine upon the earth. <hi>i. e.</hi> upon earthly Papiſts, <hi>and there fell a noiſome grievous fore upon the men that had the marke of the beaſt,</hi> upon them, and worshipped his image (<hi>i. e.</hi> upon Papiſts, which worship the Pope, and call him their Lord) and made them ſore. <hi>i. e.</hi> in conſcience, by hatred, malice, envy, railing and perſecution of the truth of <hi>Luthers</hi> Doctrine. But when <hi>Calvin</hi> I ſay had powred out a viall of Doctrine upon the See of <hi>Romes</hi> corrupt Juriſdiction and Doctrine, then the See of Rome became as the bloud of a dead man; for then they began to fill their See of Rome with blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy maſſacres, as of <hi>France, Germany, Netherlands,</hi> and the bloud of the Martyrs of <hi>England;</hi> that as when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtretched out his rod over the waters of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and all was turned into bloud, and all the fiſh in the waters dyed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.20, 21. So when <hi>Calvin</hi> the ſecond Angel had powred out his viall of Doctrine on the See of Romes diſcipline and Doctrine, they became ſo mad as to murther and maſſacre the Proteſtants, (for the Pope was more mad at <hi>Calvin</hi> then at <hi>Luther,</hi> as the Papiſts more hate the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> then the <hi>Martiniſts</hi>) then all the fiſh in the Popes See dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for their Sea was become as the bloud of a dead man: for they made all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes believe that they should merit heaven by killing the <hi>Hugonits,</hi> and they muſt doe all for the Catholike cauſe, and ſang a <hi>Te Deum</hi> for the murdering of mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Saints, and thus was the See of Rome become as the bloud of a dead man, and thus all the fish of Papiſts of the ſea of Rome dyed in the faith and in conſcience <hi>For he that hateth his Brother is a murtherer,</hi> &amp; you know that no murtherer hath eternall life, or of faith abiding in him, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.15. But all that lived in the See of Rome hate their Brethren, and are murtherers, by rejoycing at the martyrdome of the Saints of Ieſus. As for the maſſacres of <hi>France, Germany,</hi> and now in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſo that all Papiſts muſt needs dye, and cannot live by faith in the ſea of black bloud, which is alſo a ſea of Idolatry, by Idols of ſilver and gold, and wood, and ſtone, by Indulgences, pilgrimages, purgatory, prayer for &amp; to the dead, a ſea of whoredome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Re.</hi> 9.20</note> fornication, and witch-craft. How could any thing live in ſuch a corrupt ſea of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and diſcipline, when they made all guilty of the murther of Martyrs under the name of Hereticks: and they killed the life of faith into one baptiſme into Chriſts death, for remiſſion of ſins, by teaching no man could have aſſurance of ſalvation: but he muſt goe to Purgatory for his ſinnes, except it were ſuch a fish as could bring up above twenty pence in the mouth, or ſome great piece of money; ſo that as no fiſh can live <hi>mari mortuo,</hi> in the dead Sea. So no true faith can live in the dead, bloody idolatrous See of <hi>Rome.</hi> For all men may ſee, that <hi>per accidens,</hi> it was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a bloudy, dead, and rotten ſtuffe, by rejoycing at the murthers of the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified. And concerning our luke-warme ſee of Juriſdiction and Hierarchy of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:114500:11"/>
You will graunt, that it ſhall be no more; for Chriſt hath ſpewed out the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell and his Epiſcopacie out of his mouth for luke-warmene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe in faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. For they made a net of 110. articles, to have inſnared many ſoules, and to have catched many faiths in a new Oath of <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and to have tyed mens conſciences to a raile, and to cringings, and to an high Altar, and to ſo many Popes weedes of mans braine. How could any good fiſh live in ſuch pudled waters of a luke-warme ſea, but would have dyed in faith or conſcience; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe Chriſt hath ſpewed the Angell and his Hierarchie out of his mouth, there ſhall be no more luke-warme ſea. And the See of the <hi>Lutherans</hi> is become nought, and ſhall paſſe away, for it hath a name it lives, but is a dead See, lyes in a dead faith, that their workes are not perfect before God; for they hate their brethren the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> for conſubſtantiation. They ſleepe in ſinne, for they will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked out of the dead faith, though Chriſt become upon them as a Thiefe, that is, by the judgement of a robbing, killing, and deſtroying warre; for the Thiefe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not but to ſteale, and kill, and to deſtroy, <hi>John</hi> 10.10. If thou wilt not repent, and remember what thou haſt heard of (<hi>i. e.</hi> by the ſpirit of <hi>Martin Luther</hi>) and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the white raiment juſtification, to make thy workes perfect before God, and of one baptiſme into Chriſts death for remiſſion of ſinnes. Chriſt will never leave comming upon thee as a Thiefe; for he hath been upon thee as a Thiefe in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to plunder thee by a civill War, and as a Thiefe to kill thee ſometimes, man, woman, and child, &amp; he will come upon thee as a Thief to deſtroy by the Turk: For Chriſt threatened your church, that he would come on you as a Thief, and now you ſee he is come; and now ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Behold I come as a Thiefe,</hi> and therefore he will never leave comming on thee as a Thiefe: and therefore repent, and buy gold, white raiment, and eye-ſalve, or elſe the Turke will come to deſtroy thee, becauſe thou keepeſt not Chriſts garments, but walkeſt naked in ſin. Alſo the Presbyterian See of <hi>Calviniſts</hi> will be aboliſhed for ſuffering Drunkards, Uſurers, and prophane, and eſpecially <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> to ſwim in their See. Doe you not know, that the deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their firſt baptiſme was the cauſe why the Lord ſent the Turke into the church of <hi>Greece,</hi> and removed the Candleſticke of the Church out of that place, <hi>becauſe they forſooke their firſt love,</hi> i. e. their firſt baptiſme, wherein the firſt love of Chriſt is ſhewed, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p>Of the overthrow and departure of all corrupt Sees of Juriſdiction of the churches of the Gentiles, for baptiſme is good enough by whomſoever a man be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. If they have faith to believe they were then waſhed from their ſins in Chriſts bloud, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.5. <hi>For hee that believeth, and is baptized into Chriſts death for remiſſion of ſinnes, ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Mar. 16.16. It is not ſaid in mans ſtate, or in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, baptized by a faithfull Miniſter or a <hi>Judas;</hi> for <hi>ſecum valet,</hi> if he believe: for baptiſme adminiſtred in the name of the Trinity, the Father baptized, the Son bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, &amp; the holy Ghoſt baptized; for if there come true faith that they are waſhed, ſanctified, &amp; juſtified that evidence it. Now therefore if Chriſt be, and will come as a Thiefe with the Turke, upon <hi>Germany,</hi> for that greateſt Church deſtroying ſinne of the Proteſtants, for denying their firſt baptiſme, what ſhall become of your Sees then? my Text tells you they ſhall be no more, neither Epiſcopall, Presbyteriall, or Independent, but a new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and a new government from heaven.</p>
            <p>I have thought fit to admoniſh our brethren the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> that I conjecture by Scriptures that the Turke ſhall come and deſtroy <hi>Germany.</hi> Reaſon
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114500:11"/>
ſaies hee is like to come, for his Empire from ſmall beginnings hath riſen to ſuch greatneſſe by the diſcord of Chriſtians which you ſee to be in <hi>Germany,</hi> and you know that <hi>Soliman</hi> the Turke did come with 250000. men, and beſieged <hi>Vienna,</hi> but the ſins of <hi>Germany</hi> was not then full, and for the Proteſtants ſake the Turke was defeated and overthrowne by the Proteſtants, and driven out of <hi>Germany,</hi> (mark ſaith <hi>Foxe</hi> what victories God gives to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formers of Religion.) But now your ſinnes begin to be full; hee will come againe, for your ſins, and diſcord procure him. The conjunction not of ſtars, but of Scriptures I judge by, are theſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.41, 42, 43, 44. For the firſt of theſe, you know that the church of the <hi>Lutherans</hi> is the counterpain of <hi>Sardis.</hi> For you, as they have a name you live, but are dead, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the dead faith, that have no aſſurance of ſalvation by remiſſion of ſins. <hi>For you believe not your workes are perfect before God,</hi> verſ. 2. for how can you? when you live in hatred with the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> for the errour of conſubſtantiation, and they with you, <hi>v.</hi> 3. Remember both of you what you have received, <hi>i. e.</hi> one bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme into Chriſts death for remiſſion of ſinnes, and heard of <hi>Luther</hi> out of Chriſts word, of free Juſtification to make the tree good, &amp; the fruit good: but you have not held faſt your firſt baptiſme, but many among you <hi>have given heed to the doctrine of Devils, to deny your firſt love,</hi> i e. your firſt baptiſme, and have not repented of this ſin, as <hi>Epheſus</hi> did not, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Church of <hi>Greece,</hi> for which God removed the Candleſticke out of their place by the Turk. Therefore becauſe thou didſt not watch in the faith of thy baptiſme into Chriſt, he is come upon thee as a Thiefe, and will come by the Turke, and ſpoile thy Candleſtick in thy place; and thou didſt not know when he would come upon thee as a thief. Now you know that a Thief commeth not but to rob, to kill, and to deſtroy, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.10. You ſee Chriſt is come upon you with a judgement as a Thiefe, firſt to rob you, becauſe you have not kept Chriſts garments unto you by faith, that were given you in baptiſme, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. Therefore he hath been upon you with a plundering, robbing, and ſpoyling civil war, and he hath been upon you as a Thief to kil you. For many places have bin put to the ſword, men, women, and children, by <hi>Tilly</hi> and others, and he will come upon thee as a Thief to deſtroy by the Turk. <hi>For behold I come as a Thief,</hi> and therefore wil come all the 3 ways of <hi>John</hi> 10. I tell thee Chriſt will never leave comming as a Thiefe to ſteale, kill, and to deſtroy, untill thou awake out of the ſleep of this ſinne, and repent, and keep Chriſts gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto you, that you walke not naked, without a wedding garment given in baptiſme, <hi>and they ſee thy filthineſs,</hi> Rev. 16.15. And for <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.41. at the end of time, (<hi>i. e.</hi> of the churches of the Gentiles now at hand) The King of the North (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Turke ſaith <hi>Brightman,</hi> and I judge ſo too; for the Turke lyes North of the place that <hi>Daniel</hi> writ in) hee ſhall enter into the pleaſant Land (this cannot be meant of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> for the Turke hath poſſeſſed that for many yeares, <hi>Ergo,</hi> the pleaſant Land muſt be the church of Chriſtians in <hi>Germany,</hi> where is a true Church) and many countreyes ſhall be overthrowne, many churches of Idolatrous Chriſtians, beware <hi>Hungary, Poland,</hi> &amp; <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylvania,</hi> that are in his way to <hi>Germany:</hi> But theſe ſhall eſcape out of his hand, <hi>Edom,</hi> and <hi>Moab,</hi> and the chiefe of the children of <hi>Ammon.</hi> Now this cannot be meant of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Kingdomes of theſe 3. ſpoken ſo often on in Scripture, for they were deſtroyed long ſince, as the Scripture declared they ſhould be, and thoſe places are in the hands of the Turke already, from <hi>Tauris</hi> to <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Ægypt,</hi> &amp; therefore ſhall not eſcape out of the Turkes hand, as if he ſhould not come there, for thoſe places are in the Turkes hands al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, or waſte, as Geography and Scripture declare. But this is to be underſtood of the Spirituall <hi>Edom, Moab,</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> of idolatrous Chriſtians: for the ſpirituall <hi>Edom</hi> is <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly.</hi> For 1. as the <hi>Edomites</hi> came of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but were now Idolaters. So the <hi>Italians</hi> came of the Church, but are Idolaters. 2. As the <hi>Edomites</hi> were alwayes hatefull to the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:114500:12"/>
ſo are the <hi>Italians</hi> to the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> 3. As <hi>Edom</hi> would have killed <hi>Jacob,</hi> and his poſterity, was bloudy minded to the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> ſo have the <hi>Italians</hi> killed, and are blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy minded to the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> 4 As <hi>Edom</hi> rejoyced at the day of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſaving, <hi>down with it even to the ground.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 50.</note> So have the <hi>Italians</hi> at the day of the Proteſtants, of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate, Bohemia,</hi> and of <hi>Ireland,</hi> rejoyced to kill them, and ſay down with their Church even to the ground, and yet ſhall eſcape out of the hand of the Turke; for the deſtiny of <hi>Rome</hi> is to be burnt by the Proteſtants: <hi>for reward her as ſhe hath rewarded you</hi> (i. e. <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> not <hi>Turks</hi>) give her double, and in the cup ſhe filled to you (of bloud and fire) give to her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6. And the ſpirituall <hi>Moab</hi> is Idolatrous <hi>Spaine.</hi> For 1. As the <hi>Moabites</hi> were affraid the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> would eare them up, when they ſay over againſt them, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22 So have the <hi>Spaniards</hi> been affraid the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> would e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t them up that lay over againſt them. 2. As the King of <hi>Moab</hi> ſent for <hi>Balaam</hi> the falſe Prophet, that was near the children of his people, to curſe the people of God, believing he whom he bleſſeth is bleſſed, and he whom he curſeth is curſed; ſo hath the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> believed that the falſe Prophet <hi>Balaam</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> that is nigh the children of his people whom he bleſſeth or curſeth, is ſo. 3. As the King of <hi>Moab</hi> fought againſt the true church of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſo hath the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> againſt the churches of <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> 4. As wee have heard of the pride of <hi>Moab,</hi> his ſtoutneſſe and his arrogancy, <hi>Eſay</hi> 16.6. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 48. So wee have heard of the pride of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the proudeſt Nation in Chriſtendome; for onely by pride doe men make War.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro</hi> 49.</note> 5. The <hi>Moabites</hi> would not let the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> dwell with them. For the Lord ſaid, <hi>let my baniſhed dwell with thee,</hi> Iſa 16.6. but they would not. So the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> will ſuffer no Proteſtants to dwell with them. For in the Councell of <hi>Toledo,</hi> they made this Decree for the King; <hi>Nullum non Catholicum permittere in ſuo regno degere:</hi> and he that breakes that Law, that none, that is not a Catholike to permit him to live in his Kingdome, If any King ſuffer it, let him be accurſed, <hi>Maranatha,</hi> before the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God, and be made the fuell of eternall fire. I could give 20. reaſons out of Scripture why <hi>Spaine</hi> is the ſpirituall <hi>Moab,</hi> and may hereafter. And the chiefe of the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> (i. e. Of the ſpirituall <hi>Ammon</hi> of <hi>France</hi>) ſo that I cannot tell whether all <hi>France</hi> ſhall eſcape the Turke. Bloud may purſue ſome part of them for their bloudy Maſſacres, ſee <hi>Ez</hi> 35.6. <hi>Becauſe thou hateſt not bloud, bloud ſhall purſue thee</hi> For as the <hi>Ammonites</hi> would grant no life to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> at <hi>Jabeſh Gilead,</hi> but upon condition of putting out their right eyes, ſo the <hi>Ammonites</hi> of <hi>France</hi> would grant no life to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, but upon this condition of pulling out their right eye of faith, and therefore ſlew them. Secondly, As the King of <hi>Ammon</hi> abuſed the Embaſſadors of <hi>David,</hi> ſhaved off halfe their beards, cut off their garments by the butocks, &amp; ſent them away ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully entreated, ſo hath the King of <hi>France</hi> dealt with the Embaſſadorus of Jeſus Chriſt, the Miniſters of the Goſpell, ſhaved off beards, and heads, and garments, and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully entreated their. But Chriſt will avenge it. 3. As the <hi>Ammonites</hi> have been one of the greateſt enemies to the church of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in fighting and joyning againſt them: ſo have the ſpirituall <hi>Ammonites</hi> the <hi>French</hi> been againſt the Proteſtants. Witneſs the blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Maſſacre of <hi>France,</hi> Dan. 11.42. <hi>And he ſhall ſtretch out his hand on the countreys, and the Land of Aegypt ſhall not eſcape.</hi> i. e. The ſpirituall Aegypt of <hi>Germany</hi> ſhall not eſcape the <hi>Turke.</hi> For 1. as <hi>Aegypt</hi> forgat <hi>Joſeph,</hi> that had ſaved their lives by a great deliverance; ſo <hi>Germany</hi> hath forgot <hi>Fredericus</hi> Earle of <hi>Palatine,</hi> how hee ſaved their lives, and the Imperiall City <hi>Vienna,</hi> by a great deliverance, from the Turk, 1529. though he beſieged it with 20. aſſaults. 2. As the King of <hi>Aegypt</hi> ſaid, <hi>come let us deale wiſely with the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>to keepe them in bondage, leaſt they be too ſtrong for us, and if there be War, to joyne with our enemies.</hi> So hath the Emperour and his Councell plotted to deale
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114500:12"/>
wiſely with the Proteſtants, to keep them in bondage, left they ſhould be too ſtrong for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and joyn with their enemies 3. As the Aegyptians kept the Iſraelites in bondage to work in bricke and clay, and burn it, and made them weary of their lives; ſo have the <hi>Germans</hi> made the Proteſtants co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences work in brick and clay of the Maſs, and burn them in the kill of Purgatory, and have made them weary of their lives in ſerving the Papiſts Idolls 4. As the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> would not ſuffer the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to goe ſerve the Lord according to the true Religion, nor ſacrifice, nor keep a feaſt to the Lord, leſt he come upon them with peſtilence or ſword, <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.13. ſo would not the Popiſh <hi>Germans</hi> ſuffer the Proteſtants to ſerve the Lord according to his word, and keep a feaſt to the Lord, and ſacrifice in both kinds, for which he is come upon them with peſtilence and ſword. 5. As the Lord ſent 10. plagues on the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> for oppreſſing, &amp; not ſuffering the Proteſtants to ſerve the Lord, ſo hath he brought 10. plagues on the <hi>Germans,</hi> becauſe they oppreſſed, and would not ſuffer the Proteſtants to ſerve the Lord. 6. As the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> purſued the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> into the red ſea, and were drowned, ſo ſhall the <hi>Germans</hi> that have purſued the Proteſtants into the red ſea of a bloudy war, be drowned in a ſea of bloudy War. 7. As the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> when their country was overthrowne, went into <hi>Aegypt</hi> to dwell there, contrary to the Word of God, that ſaid, <hi>you ſhall return to it no more,</hi> and ſerved the Queen of heaven. Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael, <hi>behold I will ſend and bring</hi> Nebuchadnezzar <hi>King of</hi> Babel, <hi>and he ſhall ſmite the Land of</hi> Aegypt <hi>with death, captivity and ſword, and he ſhall array himſelfe in the Land of</hi> Aegypt <hi>as a Shepheard putteth on his garment, &amp; depart in peace,</hi> Jer. 43 10, 11, 12. So becauſe many Proteſtants in <hi>Germany,</hi> when their countreyes have been overthrown, are returned to <hi>Aegypt</hi> to Idolatry, whereof God hath ſaid to the Proteſtants, you ſhall return to it no more, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. But they have ſerved the Queene of heaven by <hi>Ave Maries.</hi> Now becauſe they agree in ſin, the Lord hath a King of <hi>Babel</hi> the Turk, that will ſmite the Land of <hi>Germany,</hi> and array himſelf with the land of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> as a Shepheard putteth on his garment, and return, for ſo <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.43. He ſhal have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over the treaſure of gold &amp; ſilver, and over all things of the ſpirituall <hi>Aegypt</hi> of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> &amp; departed but ſcarce in peace. For <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith that the ridings out of the Eaſt &amp; north ſhal trouble him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.44. That is, the tidings of the Eaſtern Jewes called firſt, for the 3. gates to the Eaſt ſhew it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.13. and of the Northern Jews converted. 2. that the river <hi>Euphrates</hi> ſhall be dried (as <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12.) &amp; make the laſt Jewes a paſſage into the Turkes Dominions, which ſhall trouble him, and cauſe him to return: <hi>and he ſhall go forth with great wrath to deſtroy</hi> (for it is the battel of God) and root out many: <hi>for Chriſt will dip his garments in bloud,</hi> Rev. 19.13. <hi>But he ſhall be overthrown, for he ſhall come to his end, and none ſhall help him,</hi> Dan. 11.45. For at that time <hi>Michael the great Prince that ſtandeth for the children of thy people,</hi> i. e. the Jewes. <hi>And there ſhall be a time of trouble, ſuch as never was,</hi> i. e. the hour of temptation, <hi>Re.</hi> 3.10. and thy people (the Jewes inwardly) ſhall be delivered, <hi>every one that is written in the book of life,</hi> baptized into it, &amp; believe.</p>
            <p>Now the word but, the tidings out of the Eaſt, that ſhall trouble him, muſt be when he takes the ſpoile of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> which muſt be at the time of the Jewes converſion. Therefore muſt be underſtood of another <hi>Aegypt,</hi> then that which he won, <hi>v.</hi> 5.13. When <hi>Zelimus</hi> going to war in <hi>Perſia,</hi> and <hi>Gaurius</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt</hi> troubling him, he returned ſuddenly, through <hi>Syria,</hi> &amp; ſlew the K. and took the whole kingdom of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and poſſeſſeth it to this day, and therefore ſhall not goe to take the ſpoil of his owne Country. But it muſt be underſtood of another <hi>Aegypt</hi> that he ſhall take the treaſures of, at the time of the calling of the Jews, when the tidings ſhall trouble him, &amp; that is <hi>Germany.</hi> For old <hi>Aegypt</hi> would be too near, and therefore he is like to be ſent a further journey, from the River <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> that the new Chriſtians may have better oportunity to enter into his Dominions. And
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114500:13"/>
for <hi>Edom, Moab,</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> mentioned in Scripture to come to deſtruction &amp; deſolation, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.3. They lay upon the borders of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> &amp; always troubled them. So have <hi>Spain, Italy,</hi> and <hi>France</hi> lain upon the borders of the Proteſtants, and troubled them For as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>doth God take care for Oxen?</hi> So doth God take care for <hi>Edom, Moab,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ammon,</hi> or thoſe dragons that dwell in them? as <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.3. To make mention of their eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape from the Turk, when he ſhall array himſelfe with <hi>Aegypt?</hi> for thoſe Kingdoms never were <hi>Edom, Moab<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> to the Proteſtants to trouble them. But he meaneth of the ſpirituall <hi>Moab</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> as <hi>Amandus Polanus</hi> calls it, of the ſpirituall <hi>Edom</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of the ſpirituall <hi>Ammonites</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> which lay upon the borders of the Church of Proteſtants (and have ſome people of God to goe out of them) which have been as great enemies and troublers of the Proteſtants, as theſe were of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> For what uſe should we make of the Scriptures that ſpeak of <hi>Edom, Moab,</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> If there were not ſuch <hi>Edomites, Moabites,</hi> and <hi>Ammonites,</hi> to the Proteſtants as they were. And thou <hi>London,</hi> I have been much troubled for thee, I could shew thee how thou haſt taken thy bane. Thy Epiſcopacy is fallen before <hi>Romes,</hi> and I feare thy City will. For there are 3. things that mine heart feareth, and my face is afraid of the fourth. Treaſon in a City (as firing an houſe willingly) the aſſembly of the people, and falſe accuſation (of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and truth) theſe 3. are heavier then death, <hi>Eccl</hi> 26.5. Preludiums of ruine, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion overthrows all. O thou City divided within and without: how canſt thou ſtand, &amp; Chriſt ſay true, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.25. O <hi>London</hi> wash thy heart from wickedneſs, thou maiſt be ſaved? how long shal thy wicked (and dividing) thoughts remain in thee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.14. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi> Take Chriſts counſell, to buy of him gold, white raiment, and eye-ſalve, and be zealous of theſe, and repent. <hi>For behold I ſtand at the door &amp; knocke,</hi> and will not leave knocking at the door of thy heart, except thou open the door, &amp; hear his voyce, let him in to ſup with thee &amp; thou with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18, 19, 20. You are divided for a Presbytery, &amp; and Independent government, and ſome for the old. I have counſelled you to agree, but you will not, but will have one. Well, upon theſe conditions I may conſent. Firſt you shall prove your government to be from heaven, for it is propheſied that <hi>England</hi> shall have a government from heaven, that shall laſt till the day of Doom. But I am ſure the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> comes down from heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2. and therefore the government muſt come with it. 2. That you shall find above one good Preacher for every Shire, to make your Claſſes or governors of, which if you can do, you will shame all the Parliaments that have allowed our bookes of Homilies to be a good and wholſom doctrine. For theſe are the words of the 3<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> part of the perill of Idolatry, p. 56. l. 23. It hath been continually true, &amp; will be to the worlds end, &amp; in our time, and herein our country too true, that every Shire should ſcarcely have one good Preacher, if they were divided. Mark, if there ſhall not be above one good Preacher for every ſhire, where will you find governours for your Church. 3. That none ſhall be choſen for a Governour that hath no aſſurance of ſalvation. For how ſhould hee ſet other men to heaven, which knows not whether he ſhall come there. 4. That no man ſhall be choſen a governour of a Church that is an Uſurer, or ambitiouſly deſire it, for they are moſt unfit for it, as <hi>Abimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech</hi> and <hi>Abſolom</hi> were. Therefore agree, for you have pulled down one government, and you shall not ſet up another, nor that again that you had. For I believe my Text, though you doe not: <hi>There ſhall be no more Sea.</hi> I tell you plainly you shall not ſet up, but pull down each other, til the new <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> government come down from heaven &amp; that shal be it that shall reigne. The Presbyters have overthrown the Bishops, &amp; the Independents will overthrow the Presbyters, and the Independents are divided, and shall overthrow the Anabaptiſts. But the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> shall overcome all, <hi>For there ſhall be no more Sea.</hi> Written by <hi>I. E.</hi> Paſtor of the New <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
